Okay, בוקר טוב. Boker Tov. Today's דף daf is דף צז Daf
Tzadi Zayin and we start with a new and exciting topic. We
pick up from two lines from the bottom of צ"ו עמוד ב,
Tzadi Vav Amud Bet, 96B. אמר ליה רב נחמן לרב יצחק. Amar
leh Rav Nachman le-Rav Yitzchak. It's not exactly clear what how this
is a continuation of what came before. Before, to remind you, was
the whole discussion about the fall of well first we started with
סנחריב Sancheriv and then נבוכדנצר Nevuchadnezzar and the fall of them. And
now the גמרא Gemara is going to turn into a focused discussion
of when משיח Mashiach will come, which is very relevant to this
פרק, perek, which is about, you know, עולם הבא, Olam Ha-Ba, ימות
המשיח, Yemos Ha-Mashiach, but not exactly clear how it's a continuation of
the past. Unless, you know, the past was a focus on those
that came to war against us and were the onset of the
גלות Galus and now we're raising the question: when will משיח Mashiach
come? So אמר ליה רב נחמן לרב יצחק. amar leh Rav Nachman
le-Rav Yitzchak. רב נחמן Rav Nachman said to רב יצחק, Rav Yitzchak,
two lines from the bottom, צ"ו עמוד ב: Tzadi Vav Amud Bet:
מי שמיע לך אימת אתי בר נפלי? Mi shemeia lekha eimat ati
Bar Nafli? Do you know when the son of Nafli will come?
אמר ליה מאן בר נפלי? Amar leh, man Bar Nafli? Who do
you mean? Who is this בר נפלי? Bar Nafli? אמר ליה משיח.
Amar leh, Mashiach. I refer to משיח. Mashiach. אמר ליה, Amar leh,
so משיח בר נפלי קרית ליה? Mashiach Bar Nafli karit leh? You're
calling משיח Mashiach the son of Nafli, which presumably means the son
of those who have fallen? אמר ליה אין. Amar leh, in. Yes.
דכתיב ביום ההוא אקים את סוכת דויד הנופלת. De-khtiv: Ba-yom ha-hu akim
et sukkat David ha-nofelet. At that day, I will raise up the
fallen סוכה, sukkah, the fallen, you know, dominion, kingship of King דויד.
David. So again, interesting because you normally want to emphasize that משיח
Mashiach will be the positive that משיח Mashiach will bring, but here
it is sort of saying it will ultimately be what will be
resulting from our, you know, our hardship and our suffering and so
on and this will be the thing that will emerge from it
will be the
משיח. Mashiach. הכי אמר רבי יוחנן. Hakhi amar Rabbi Yochanan. Here's what
רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan said. דור שבן דוד בא בו. Dor she-ben
David ba bo. The generation that the son of דוד David will
come, that משיח Mashiach will come, בו תלמידי חכמים מתמעטין. bo talmidei
chakhamim mitmatin. The תורה Torah sages will be diminished. The number of
them will be shrinking. So you can't make that work for nowadays
because of the tremendous proliferation of ישיבות yeshivot nowadays. והשאר עיניהם כלות
ביגון ואנחה. Ve-ha-shear eineihem kalot be-yagon ve-anachah. And the rest of the
people, their eyes will be, you know, dimmed with anguish and moaning.
וצרות רבות וגזירות קשות מתחדשות, Ve-tzarot rabbot ve-gezeirot kashot mitchadshot, and tremendous
afflictions and edicts against the Jewish people will be, you know,
come
like
fast and furious. עד שראשונה פקודה שניה ממהרת לבוא. Ad she-rishonah pekudah,
shniyah mimaheret lavo. Before the first one is done, you know, the
first one hasn't even finished the effects of the first tragedy or
edict against the Jewish people and even before that's over, the next
one is already on its way coming. So it'll be a time
of tremendous difficulty and struggle. By the way, which fits a lot
with the calling about בר נפלי, Bar Nafli, fallen, you know, that
actually the time leading up to it will be a time of
great tragedy. תנו רבנן. Tanu rabbanan. Our rabbis taught. שבוע שבן דוד
בא. Shavua she-ben David ba. The שמיטה shmita cycle in which משיח
Mashiach will come, שנה ראשונה מתקיים מקרא זה. shanah rishonah mitkayem mikra
zeh. The first year will be a fulfillment of this פסוק: pasuk:
והמטרתי על עיר אחת ועל עיר אחרת לא אמטיר. Ve-himtarti al ir
achat ve-al ir acheret lo amtir. I will cause it to rain
on one city and not another city, meaning that there will be
sporadic rainfall, there will be some cities will have it good, some
cities will be in famine. שניה, Shniyah, the second year, חצי רעב
משתלחים. chitzei ra'av mishtalchim. Everybody will suffer pangs of hunger. There will
be, you know, won't be starvation, but it will be
a year of privation.
שלישית רעב גדול. Shlishit ra'av gadol. By the third year, it'll be
a great famine. ומתים אנשים ונשים וטף וחסידים ואנשי מעשה ותורה משתכחת
מלומדיה. U-metim anashim ve-nashim ve-taf ve-chasidim ve-anshei ma'aseh ve-Torah mishtakachat mi-lomdeha. And
it'll be a year in which men, women, and children die, and,
you know, the righteous and people of good deeds, you know, also
presumably will
die, and the תורה Torah will be forgotten from those who have
learned it because they'll just be so overwhelmed with the hunger. ברביעית,
Ba-revit, in the fourth year, שובע ואינו שובע. sova ve-eino sova. It
will be a year of being sated and not fully sated, meaning
now the pendulum is swinging up. So the we're still have a
degree of privation, but also things are getting better. בחמישית, Ba-chamishit, שובע
גדול. sova gadol. By the fifth year, it'll be great satiation. ואוכלין
ושותין ושמחין
ותורה חוזרת ללומדיה. Ve-okhlin ve-shotin ve-smekhin ve-Torah chozeret le-lomdeha. And they will
eat and drink and
rejoice, and the תורה Torah will return to those who had learned
it. So it's sort of like, you know, it's like a U-shaped
curve here.
ותורה חוזרת ללומדיה. Ve-Torah chozeret le-lomdeha. ובששית קולות. U-va-shishit kolot. In the
sixth year, there will be sounds. Not exactly clear what those sounds
are. רש"י Rashi says maybe it means sounds... heralding the coming of
the
משיח Mashiach. *Mashiach* and בשביעית מלחמות *bishvi'is milchamos* that will be when
the great wars will take place and
maybe presumably the war of גוג ומגוג Gog u'Magog. *Gog u-Magog* and
finally במוצאי שביעית *bemotzei shvi'is* at the end of the seventh year
בן דוד Ben David, בא *ben David ba* the משיח Mashiach *Mashiach*
will come. So people could if you wanted to if people were
so inclined you could try to read this metaphorically and not just
limiting to seven
years about how things got worse and worse in if you wanted
to read it in a contemporaneous lens how things got like worse
and worse in Europe before leading up to the World War I
mean the Holocaust and then of course things like the third year
was the Holocaust where men women and children died and תורה Torah
*Torah* was תורה Torah *Torah* communities were destroyed and then as Israel
sort of rebuilds after the Holocaust sort of see that as like
the upward arc. So anyway interesting way possible way if somebody were
so inclined to read it that way. Anyway that's how he says
the seven year cycle leading up.
So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says אמר אביי Amar Abaye: *Amar Abaye*
I'm sorry so אמר רב amar Rav, יוסף *Amar Rav Yosef* so
רב Rav יוסף *Rav Yosef* says הא כמה שביעיתא דהוה כן ולא
v'lo, אתא *ha kama shevi'isa dahava ken velo asa* we had a
couple of שמיטה *Shmita* cycles where this happened and משיח Mashiach, *Mashiach*
didn't come. Now we're going to see in a minute that obviously
the whole thing didn't happen some pieces of it happened. So אמר
amar אביי *Amar Abaye* אביי *Abaye* said back בששית קולות בשביעית מלחמות
מי הוה *bishishis kolos bishvi'is milchamos mi hava*? First of all it's
not true. Maybe you had some years that were bad and famine
and other years that were good but you didn't have the culmination
of this the sixth year these sounds heralding the משיח Mashiach *Mashiach*
or whatever the sounds mean and the seventh year the wars that
never happened. ועוד כסידרן מי הוה *ve-od kesidran mi hava*? And also
didn't happen in the order that was described just like exactly like
U-shaped arc here okay you had some years were like this some
were like that but it was not the order it was not
the exact sequence described here. All right. The other point is just
because it says that's what it will happen before משיח Mashiach. *Mashiach*
comes doesn't mean that when it happens משיח Mashiach. *Mashiach* will definitely
come. But anyway the point being it didn't happen. Okay תניא Tanya,
*Tanya* we taught רבי יהודה אומר omer,
*Rabbi Yehuda omer* we'll skip the parenthesis דור שבן דוד בא Dor
sheBen David ba, בו bo, בית וועד יהיה לזנות *dor she-ben David
ba bo beis va'ad yehi leznus* the generation that the that משיח
Mashiach, *Mashiach* will come the house of gathering of where like the
בית המדרש *Beis HaMedrash* where the sages would gather will turn into
a place of fornication a prostitution. והגליל יחרב *ha-Galil yecherav* the Galilee
will be destroyed והגבלן יישם *ve-ha-Gavlan ye'asham* and the גבלן *Gavlan* will
be also laid desolate. גבלן *Gavlan* is to some refers to sort
of like the גולן *Golan* or up north הר חרמון *Har Chermon*.
Again interesting for those would be so inclined to read this in
a contemporary lens about the northern cities that have been
now made desolate or whatever because of because of the war that
it's going on in the northern border. ואנשי גבול יסובבו מעיר לעיר
ולא יחוננו *ve-anshei gvul yesovevu me-ir le-ir velo yechanunu* what really caught
my attention was this next line ואנשי גבול יסובבו מעיר לעיר ולא
יחוננו *ve-anshei gvul yesovevu me-ir le-ir velo yechanunu* and the people of
the border cities will travel from city to city and will never
won't be sort of settled and at rest. And if that's not
describing what happened to those living near Gaza and those in the
north I mean that's really got to catch your attention. וחכמת סופרים
תסרח *ve-chochmas hasofrim tisrach* the wisdom of the sages will be spoiled.
ויראי חטא ימאסו *ve-yirei cheit yim'asu* those who fear sin will be
held will be despised. So people's values will be all turned upside
down. ופני הדור כפני כלב ufnei hador kepnei kelev, *u-pnei hador kipnei
kelev* and the face of the generation will be like the face
of a dog. Not exactly clear what that means. מהרש"א Maharsha *Maharsha*
sort of says it means dogs always sort of show friendliness and
loyalty but that's only the way they're
appearing really behind that there's betrayal. והאמת נעדרת ve-ha-emet ne’ederet, *ve-ha-emes ne'ederes*
and truth will be absent and lost. Certainly something I think some
people are feeling sort of nowadays how perverse perverse the certain values
and certain things have gotten and what really represents
truth everything is a fake fact if you don't like it fake
news if you don't like it do we really have common standards
of truth anymore?
שנאמר she-ne'emar
*shene'emar* as the פסוק pasuk *pasuk* says ותהי האמת נעדרת *vatehi ha-emes
ne'ederes* and truth will be lost. מאי ותהי האמת נעדרת *mai vatehi
ha-emes ne'ederes*? ותהי האמת נעדרת *vatehi ha-emes ne'ederes* וסר מרע משתולל *v'sar
meira mishtolel* and the one who turns from evil
will be mocked. That's the end of the פסוק pasuk? *pasuk* we'll
get back to that. מאי ותהי האמת נעדרת *mai vatehi ha-emes ne'ederes*
truth will be lost? אמרי דבי רב *amri d'bei Rav* מלמד שנעשית
עדרים עדרים והולכת לה *melamed shena'asis adarim adarim ve-holeches lah* like gather
up into flocks and it'll wander away. So it's not exactly clear
why it reads it that way rather than just it means that
it'll be
lost but the מהרש"א Maharsha *Maharsha* explains that if it refers to
תורה Torah. *Torah* and תלמידי חכמים talmidei chachamim *Talmidei Chachamim*
it doesn't mean that it'll totally be absent. but it means that
they will like abandon, you know,
the place where most people are because the because the the generation
has become so corrupt and they'll have to like go off into
the wilderness and find places of their own. Okay,
where were we? Okay, וחלופה. מאי וסר מרע משתולל? mai v’sar me-ra
mishtolel? אמרי דבי רבי שילא amri devei Rabbi Shila כל מי שסר
מרע משתולל על הבריות. kol mi she-sar me-ra mishtolel al ha-briyot. Anybody
that turns away from evil will be, you know, will be seen
like a fool as far through the eyes of the population. Okay,
so anything good, anything positive will be looked at as evil and
as stupid.
על הבריות. al ha-briyot. אמר רבא amar Rava מריש הוה אמינא לית
קושטא בעלמא. me-reish hava amina leit kushta b’alma. I used to say
there's no real truth in this world. This is, you know, this
is a world of שקר, sheker, everything gets perverted, nobody can really
stand fully by the principle of truth.
This is based again on the פסוק pasuk. of והאמת נעדרת, you
know, truth is lost. So he says לית קושטא בעלמא. leit kushta
b’alma.
אמרי
לי ההוא מרבנן amri li hahu me-rabbanan so one of these rabbis,
a certain one of the rabbinical students, רב טבות שמיה Rav Tavut
shemei and some say רב טביומי שמיה, Rav Tavyomi shemei, דאי הוו
יהבי ליה כל חללא דעלמא de-ee havu yahavi leh kol chalala d’alma
and this rabbi, you know, said that if somebody would give him
all of this, you know, wealth of the world, you know, the
entire fill of the world, לא הוה משני בדבוריה, lo hava meshanei
be-dibburei, it would not be enough to make him ever misrepresent himself,
say an untruth. ולא הוה משני בדבוריה. ve-lo hava meshanei be-dibburei. זימנא
חדא איקלע לההוא אתרא zimna chada i-kla le-hahu atra
and he basically and what he said to me was the following
that one time I came to a certain place וקושטא שמיה ve-kushta
shemei the name of the place was Truth. ולא הוו משני בדבורייהו
ve-lo havu meshanei be-dibbureihu
and nobody there ever slightly fudged anything. Everybody stood for a hundred
percent truth. ולא הוי מיית אינש מהתם בלא זימניה ve-lo havay me-yeis
inash me-hasam be-lo zimnei and nobody died there before his, you know,
before his ripe age. נסיבי איתתא מינהון nesivi iteta mineihon
so this rabbi said I married a woman from
there and basically I settled there. והוו לי תרין בנין מינה ve-havu
li terein banin minah and I had and I had two sons.
יומא חד הוה יתבא דביתהו וקא חייפא רישא yoma chad hava yatva
deveisahu ve-ka chayfa reisha
and one day like this wife was sitting and washing her hair.
אתאי שיבבתא טרפא בדשא asai shivavta tarfa be-dasha and a neighbor came,
knocked on the door. סבר savar or סברי savri I thought, okay
question who's telling this story is, you know, is רבא Rava telling
the story or the person telling the story on his own? It's
like different versions of what the grammar here is. I thought or
he thought. Anyway we'll have him do it until telling it. I
thought לאו אורח ארעא lav orach ara it's not appropriate to say
my wife is in the bathroom, my wife is in the shower.
So אמר so I said or he said אמרי לה amri lah
so I said to the neighbor ליתא הכא leisa hacha she's not
here. שכיבו ליה תרין בנין shichivu leh terein banin it now goes
back to the third person so it sounds more like רבא Rava
saying this. His so anyway he said she's not here and his
two sons died. So this is like a classic trope you know
whatever that your a person's children can die due to his sins,
we won't get into that whole you know challenging theology, but bottom
line is here he was he misrepresented and that brought death and
he fudged the truth and that brought death into his household and
obviously before their time. They died before their father. אתו אינשי דאתרא
לקמיה asu inshi de-asra lekamei
so the people of the city came to him. אמרו ליה amru
leh and said to him מאי האי mai hai what's happening here?
אמר להו amar lehu he said to them הכי הוה מעשה hachi
hava maaseh here's what happened, I fudged it a little because I
wanted to spare my wife's privacy and this is what happened. אמרו
ליה amru leh so they said to him במטותא מינך be-matusa minach
please you know with your permission or like do us a favor
פוק מאתרא puk me-asra and please leave our place ולא תגרי בהו
מותנא בהני אינשי ve-lo tigrei behu mosana be-hanei inshi and do not
sort of incite that against those people meaning don't bring death into
our city. Okay, so here was this person that that's what happened
once because he slightly fudged something to protect somebody, to protect his
wife's privacy, so now he has basically taken this oath that he
will, you know, or taken this position that he will no matter
what anybody gives him he will never again misrepresent anything. You know,
of course it's a little funny because the גמרא Gemara says you
are allowed to like misrepresent for things like כבוד הבריות kevod ha-briyot
and so on. So maybe that's what רבא Rava means when he
says that there's no truth in the world. Maybe it's not a
bemoaning that there's no truth but maybe it's actually,
you know, like like again it's hard to see where that is
in this story but like but like
you know I you're left with this story I think I'm left
with this story I should say wondering which is like okay according
to the story his sons died and that says you should always
tell the harsh truth. But really? like, you're not supposed to protect
people's privacy? And we know that the גמרא Gemara says you are
allowed to fudge for certain things. So I'm left very confused what
the message ultimately is. Okay, anyway, the גמרא Gemara continues. תניא, Tanya,
we learned in a ברייתא. Braisa.
רבי נהוראי Rebbi Nehorai אומר, omer, back to משיח. Moshiach דור שבן
דוד בא, dor sheBen David ba, in the generation that משיח Moshiach
will come, בו, נערים ילבינו פני זקנים, nearim yalbinu pnei zekenim, this
is a גמרא Gemara in סוטה, Sotah, most people know it from,
again, it'll be a generation of similar to before, where like truth
will be despised and good will be despised. So here also, a
דור dor of חוצפה, chutzpah,
of lack of showing proper respect, of temerity, of despising those who
are deserved to be honored. So נערים ילבינו פני זקנים, nearim yalbinu
pnei zekenim, the youth will cause to blanch the face of the
elders, they'll embarrass the older, וזקנים יעמדו לפני נערים, uzekenim yaamdu lifnei
nearim, it'll be expected that the elders will rise in front of
the youth as opposed to the reverse. So age will not be
respected. ובת קמה באמה, uvas kama be'ima, a daughter will rise up
against her mother, וכלה בחמותה, vekala bachamosah, and a daughter-in-law against her
mother-in-law, ופני הדור כפני כלב, the face of the generation is like
the face of a dog, we discussed it already, ואין הבן מתבייש
מאביו, ve'ein haben misbayesh me'aviv, and a son will not be embarrassed
in the presence of his fathers. Interesting what it ascribes to sons,
what to daughters. Anyway, תניא, Tanya, we learned in a ברייתא, Braisa,
רבי נחמיה Rebbi Nechemiah אומר, דור שבן דוד בא, in the generation
when the son of David comes, בו העזות תרבה, bo haazut tirbeh,
the brazenness will increase, והיוקר יעוות, vehayoker yaaves, that that
which is honored will be the way one way רש״י Rashi reads
this, it says proper showing of honor will be perverted. והיוקר יעוות,
vehayoker yaaves, הגפן תתן פריו, hagefen titein piryo, the vine will give
its fruit, והיין ביוקר vehayayin beyoker and nevertheless, הגפן תתן פריו hagefen
titein piryo is the one positive thing. So it has to be
read together with the next line: although the wine will give its
fruit, although there will be a lot of grapes, והיין ביוקר, vehayayin
beyoker, the wine will be very expensive. Probably the best read of
this is what רש״י Rashi says means: there'll be plenty of wine
around, but everybody will be so drunk and there will be such
high demand that wine will be very expensive. ונהפכה כל המלכות למינות,
venehepcha kol hamalchus leminus, and the entire
kingdom will turn to heresy.
Not exactly clear what this means about the idea of heresy, because
they were under the rule of the Roman government, and do they
mean that it will turn to Christianity?
מין, min, so it probably refers heresy as opposed to עבודה זרה,
avodah zarah, because the Christians, because the Romans were pagans and worked
עבודה זרה. avodah zarah. Heresy often refers in the גמרא Gemara to
Christianity, it's a type of a Jewish heresy. So this means that
the
entire Roman government will turn to Christianity. Now, רבי נחמיה Rebbi Nechemiah
lived in the second century, and Constantine that did convert the entire
Roman Empire into Christianity was in the beginning of the fourth century.
So actually, he maybe had a sense that that's where things were
going and said that when that happens,
maybe that's not sufficient by itself, but that is one of the
signs of the coming of the משיח, Moshiach although it's been many,
many years since that piece of it has happened. Okay, anyway, ואין
תוכחה, ve'ein tochechah,
and nobody will be, and there'll be no rebuke, nobody will listen
to rebuke. מסייע ליה לרבי יצחק, mesayei lei leRebbi Yitzchak,
this teaching of רבי נחמיה Rebbi Nechemiah supports the teaching of רבי
יצחק, Rebbi Yitzchak, דאמר רבי יצחק, deamar Rebbi Yitzchak, אין בן דוד
בא עד שתתהפך כל המלכות למינות. ein Ben David ba ad shetis'hapech
kol hamalchus leminus. Now for רבי יצחק, Rebbi Yitzchak, he is the
only for him sign of or necessary thing to happen for משיח
Moshiach to come. So that happened about 1,700 years ago, so we're
still waiting for משיח. Moshiach אמר רבא מאי קרא, amar Rava mai
kra, what's the פסוק? pasuk כולו הפך לבן טהור הוא. kulo hapach
lavan tahor hu. If it all turns white, right? So like the
צרעת, tzaraas, the leprosy, the bad thing, if it spreads completely, then
that's a sign of something positive.
Okay, I don't know what to make of that. תנו רבנן, tanu
rabanan, כי ידין ה׳ עמו, ki yadin Hashem amo, God will judge
his people. Here we're reading like when the true judgment will come
and it'll be the time for משיח. Moshiach, כי יראה כי אזלת
יד, ki yireh ki azlas yad, he will see that there they
have lost power, ואפס עצור ועזוב, ve'efes atzur ve'azuv, and there is
none that is, sort of, guarding them and none to be helped
and supported. So what does this tell us? אין בן דוד בא
עד שירבו המסורות. ein Ben David ba ad sheyirbu hamesoros. בן דוד,
ben David the משיח, Moshiach won't come until those that hand over
the Jews to the government become greatly increased,
maybe reading אזלת יד azlas yad like the hand will be reached
out against them. דבר אחר עד שימעטו התלמידים, davar acher ad sheyime'atu
hatalmidim,
until the תלמידים, talmidim, the תלמידי חכמים are decreased, and that of
course we have seen before, and that certainly as רש״י Rashi points
out, that's like there is none that
is strengthening them because תורה Torah would strengthen them. דבר אחר Davar
acheir עד שתכלה פרוטה מן הכיס, ad she-tichleh perutah min ha-kis, there
is no money to be found in the pocket, so that’s רש״י
Rashi says אזלת יד azlat yad like your hand in your pocket
you don’t have any money, so there’s no available funds. דבר אחר
Davar acheir עד שיתייאשו מן הגאולה, ad she-yityashu min ha-geulah, until they
and that maybe is even the closest sense of the פסוק. pasuk
You know there's like nothing is there to save and to hold
them and it's at that time of greatest despair that's when they
and the greatest of loss of hope that redemption will
come, שנאמר she-ne'emar ואפס עצור ועזוב. ve-efes atzur ve-azuv. כביכול kibi-yachol אין
סומך ועוזר לישראל, ein somech ve-ozer le-Yisrael, it will be in their
eyes as if there is none that is supporting and helping Israel,
that's the way they will feel and at that moment משיח Moshiach
will come. אמר רבי זירא, Amar Rabbi Zeira, like what Rabbi Zeira
taught, כי הא דמשכח רבנן דהוו עסקי בה ki ha de-mashkach rabbanan
de-havu iskei bei when he found Rabbis that were very like engaged
in it in trying to figure out when משיח Moshiach. will come.
I mean look, you see the fact that
the Gemara is giving all of these signposts, you know, and we'll
get to a minute people that are actually trying to make certain
פסוקים pesukim compute the exact years. You know, this is something that
went on for a good long time. If you're a people living
as oppressed and in exile, you want and you have the belief
of the משיח Moshiach is what sort of gives you hope for
the future. That's going to lead to a certain preoccupation at times
with the question about what will happen when משיח Moshiach comes, you
know, what what are things going to look like and when is
it going to come and let's try to compute when it's going
to come. So he said when I would find the Rabbis that
they were involving themselves in this and trying to figure out when
משיח Moshiach would come, אמר להו amar lehu I would say to
them, I'm sorry, when Rabbi Zeira would find the Rabbis doing this,
אמר להו amar lehu he would say to the Rabbis, the rabbinical
students, במטותא bi-metuta like you know like with your permission or please
do me a favor, בעינא מינייכו baina minaikhu let me I ask
from you, לא תרחקוה, lo terachakuha, do not make it even like
push it off even further. So the more you involve yourself in
trying to figure out when it's going to come, the longer it's
going to take to come. And this isn't just a principle of
like you know a watched pot never boils or maybe it is,
דתניא de-tanya because we taught in a ברייתא, braita, ג' באים בהיסח
הדעת Gimel ba'im be-hesech ha-da'at three things come if you don't pay
attention to them. אלו הן Elu hen and these are they, משיח,
Moshiach מציאה, metziah, ועקרב. ve-akrav. You find a lost object if you
go around looking for to find a מציאה, metziah, you're not going
to find it. If you're just going by your daily activities and
that's when you'll trip over a lost object. But also if you're
not paying attention a scorpion will come and bite you and that's
the עקרב. akrav. So not exactly clear what the lesson here is.
I mean מהרש״א Maharsha tries to connect the three by saying you
know based on what are things going to look like when משיח
Moshiach comes, will it be a good period or bad period? Are
you going to be rewarded, are you going to be punished? Will
it be a מציאה metziah or will it be an עקרב? akrav?
But still not exactly clear what means that like you know it
comes by not paying attention to it. But I think the point
is is that is besides like he's basically saying you know these
computations are a waste of time, but they also distract us from
what our work is in this world. You know the importance of
a whole belief of of משיח Moshiach is it gives us you
know is that that's the time when like justice will be served
and that gives us hope when we are oppressed and all of
that, but you know Judaism and תורה Torah and מצוות mitzvos has
always been very very much a this-worldly religion. So if you're just
waiting for that future time, are you really doing fully and investing
fully in the work that you have to be doing right now
to hopefully bring the משיח. Moshiach Although that shouldn't be your motivation,
but if you focus on what you need to be doing right
now, that'll help the משיח Moshiach come sooner rather than later. אמר
רב קטינא, Amar Rav Katina, שית אלפי שני הוי עלמא. sheis alfei
shani havei alma. Now
right after saying don't spend your time trying to figure out when
משיח Mashiach is going to come, now we're going to have certain
computations. The world has an this is extremely well known by people,
you know, the world has a 6,000 year lifespan. שית אלפי שני
הוי עלמא sheis alfei shani havei alma וחד חרוב ve-chad charuv
and 1,000 years after the 6,000 everything will be destroyed and then
there will be a new world created. We've already had this before,
you know, and that will be the time of משיח Mashiach, or
the עולם הבא, Olam ha-Ba, שנאמר ונשגב ה' לבדו ביום ההוא, Shene'emar
venisgav Hashem levado bayom hahu, God will stand alone on that day.
So and we'll see in a minute a פסוק pasuk, that one
day of God is a thousand years. So but presumably reading like
after that day or no that excuse me for that day for
that thousand years it will be God alone, all of creation, the
whole world will be destroyed and then a new world will come
into existence after that thousand years. אביי אמר, Abaye amar, תרי חרוב
terei charuv 2,000 years it'll be destroyed, שנאמר she-ne'emar יחיינו מיומיים, yechayeinu
mi-yomayim,
God will bring us alive after two days, ביום השלישי יקימנו ba-yom
ha-shlishi yekimenu or יחיינו, yechayeinu, like the תחיית המתים techiyat ha-meitim will
happen, but somehow at the end of two days, meaning 2,000 years,
on the third day and the third thousand year, that is when
we will rise up from the dead, that will be the ימות
המשיח yemot ha-Moshiach ונחיה לפניו ve-nichyeh le-fanav and we'll live in God's
presence. תני כוותיה דרב קטינא, Tani kevasei de-Rav Katina, we taught like
Rav Katina. כשם שהשביעית משמטת שנה אחת לשבע שנים, Keshem she-hashevi'is meshametes
shanah achas le-shiva shanim,
the same way the sabbatical year is one year out of seven,
it's like fallow. ככה עולם משמט אלף שנים לשבעת אלפין שנים. Kacha
olam meshamet elef shanim l'shivas alfin shanim. The world also will be
fallow for a thousand years every seven thousand years. שנאמר ונשגב ה'
לבדו ביום ההוא, ve-nisgav Hashem levado ba-yom ha-hu, God alone will be
during that time. ואומר מזמור שיר ליום השבת יום שכולו שבת. Ve'omer
Mizmor Shir Leyom Hashabbos, yom shekulo Shabbos. The idea would be a
day of complete rest.
Now when we think of a day of complete rest and we
pray for עולם הבא, Olam Haba, you know, שבת Shabbos is מעין
עולם הבא. me'ein Olam Haba. I don't think we're talking about a
destroyed world.
So it's a little conflicting ideas of you know what we mean
about this, you know, יום שכולו שבת, yom shekulo Shabbos, because here
it is sounding much more sort of destructive than the perfect edenic
type of world. ואומר Ve'omer and it says כי אלף שנים בעיניך
כיום אתמול כי יעבור. ki elef shanim be'einecha kiyom esmol ki ya'avor.
Anyway, but after that thousand years of complete rest, that's when משיח
Mashiach. will come. תנא דבי אליהו Tana d'vei Eliyahu presumably,
that that is what it is saying and that's certainly what the
גמרא Gemara. said before. Okay. תנא דבי אליהו ששת אלפי שני הוי
עלמא. Tana d'vei Eliyahu sheishes alfei shanei havei alma. The world is
six thousand years. Now we're going to divide it into epochs. שני
אלפים תוהו, Shnei alafim tohu, two thousand years emptiness, you know, of
void and empty because that was two thousand years from the beginning
of creation until you know אברהם. Avraham. אברהם Avraham was born in
the year 1948 from creation of the world, you know, going by
conventional chronology. And רש"י Rashi says, you know, the idea says ואת
הנפש אשר עשו בחרן, ve'es hanefesh asher asu vecharan, that they brought
converts, you know, the traditional teaching they brought converts to under כנפי
השכינה, kanfei haShechinah, to recognize God when אברהם Avraham himself recognized God.
רש"י Rashi said we'll say that that'll be at the when he
was 52 years old. So at the year 2000. So until that
moment of when אברהם Avraham now is launching on his
career and and has discovered God and has brought people closer to
God, until that world is like a desolate world
and that's the first two thousand years. רמב"ן Ramban on בראשית Bereishis
tries to say, you know, the תוהו tohu of course evokes תוהו
ובוהו. tohu vavohu. So רמב"ן Ramban on בראשית Bereishis tries to link
not just here we're
going to divide things into epochs of two thousand years, but there
he tries to divide the world into epochs of one thousand years
and have each thousand correspond to its day of creation. Okay, but
anyway two thousand years of תוהו, tohu, שני אלפים תוהו. Shnei alafim
tohu. For the next two thousand are תורה. Torah Why? Well again,
it starts with אברהם Avraham and שרה Sarah bringing people under כנפי
השכינה, kanfei haShechinah, bringing them close to God, close to whatever, what
would be you know beginning of תורה and מצוות, mitzvos, to be
obviously then finally through מעמד הר סיני. Ma'amad Har Sinai. So that's
the time the period of the Jewish people of our close relationship
to God, getting direction, getting מצוות, mitzvos, ultimately
standing at הר סיני. Har Sinai. And that goes for two thousand
years. And if you do the math, where that two thousand years
gets us is the year 4000. That is about the year
250 of the common era. So and that is the end of
the period of the תנאים. Tanna'im. Okay, so the beginning of the
period of the גמרא. Gemara, So that is the period filled with
מצוות mitzvos and תורה and so on. Now שני אלפים ימות המשיח,
shnei alafim yemot haMoshiach, the two thousand years after doesn't mean that
תורה stops, but the two thousand years after now we're entering into
a period where it's possible משיח Mashiach will come, which is pretty
much the period that he was in when he was talking, right,
was was just after that period of the תנאים. Tanna'im. Okay. Top
of צדיק ז' עמוד ב'. Tzadik Zayin amud beis. ובעוונותינו שרבו, Uvavonoseinu
sherabu, but in our great iniquity יצאו מהם מה שיצאו. yatze'u mehem
mah she-yatze'u. So you know the years that have in this last
period of two thousand years, you know, משיח Mashiach could come at
the beginning of that period and now we're you know a few
hundred years into it or few whatever how many years into it,
so those are lost opportunities. Because of our sins it hasn't come
so far in those years, but it's sometime in this two thousand
year period where it could still come.
אמר ליה אליהו לרב יהודה, Amar lei Eliyahu l'Rav Yehuda, רב יהודה
אחוה דרב סילא. Rav Yehuda achva deRav Sila. אליהו Eliyahu said to
רב יהודה, Rav Yehuda, the brother of of רב סילא, Rav Sila,
חסידא, chasida, the חסיד, chasid, אין עולם פחות משמונים וחמשה יובלות. ein
olam pachot mishmonim vachamisha yovlot. The world is no will be no
less than
85 יובלות. yovlot. Now if you just do the math, right, 50
years to the יובל, yovel, 80 is 4000, so that gets us
exactly back to the same computation. But he adds another five, 250.
So משיח Mashiach can't come until about the year, you know, 500
and forward. וביובל האחרון בן דוד בא. Uvyovel ha'acharon ben David ba.
And the last יובל, yovel, that's when בן דוד will come. Of
course that did not happen. That would have been about the year
500. אמר ליה, בתחילתו או בסופו, Amar lei b'tchilaso o b'sofo, will
it be at the beginning of that יובל yovel or at the
end of it? אמר ליה, איני יודע. Amar lei eini yodea, I
don't know. כלו או אינו כלו, Kalu o eino kalu, will the
period be finished first and then משיח Mashiach will come or will
he come during that period? אמר ליה, איני יודע. Amar lei eini
yodea, I don't know. רב אשי אמר. Rav Ashi amar. אמר ליה
Amar lei, בתחילתו או בסופו, bitchilaso o besofo, will it be at
the beginning of that יובל Yovel or at the end of it?
אמר ליה Amar lei, איני יודע, eini yodeia. I don't know. כלו
או אינו כלו, Kalo o ein kalo, will the period be finished
first and then the משיח Mashiach will come or will he come
during that period? אמר ליה Amar lei, איני יודע, eini yodeia. I
don't know. רב אשי אמר הכי אמר ליה, Rav Ashi amar hachi
amar lei, this is what he said to him: עד הכא לא
תיסתכי ליה, Ad hacha lo tistachi lei, before this time, before the
year, let's call it 500, don't anticipate the משיח, Moshiach don't like,
you know, wait for it. It ain't gonna come before the year
500. מכאן ואילך, Mikan v'eilach, from that point on, איסתכי ליה, istachi
lei, you should look forward to it, meaning it'll—it's not going to
come after year 500 in that last יובל, Yovel, but it will
come any point from that point onward. Okay. שלח ליה רב חנא
בר תחליפא לרב
יוסף, Shelach lei Rav Chana bar
Tachlipa l'Rav Yosef, so Rav Chana bar Tachlipa sent to Rav Yosef:
מצאתי אדם אחד ובידו מגילה אחת, Matzasi adam echad u'vyado megilla achas,
I found a certain person, man, might not even be Jewish, and
he was carrying a scroll, כתובה אשורית ובלשון הקודש, Kesuva Ashuris u'v'lashon
hakodesh, and it was written in אשורית, Ashuris, which is our Hebrew
writing, not the ancient Hebrew writing, but the one like in the
גמרא, Gemara the classic one that we use, and—and in Hebrew. So
he had—here was a non-Jew had stumbled across some ancient Hebrew scroll.
אמרתי לו מזו מניין לך, Amarti lo mizo minayin lach, where did
you get this? אמר לי, Amar li, he said to me, לחיילות
של רומי נשכרתי, L'chayilos shel Romi niskarti, I have—I'm like a—you know,
a—what's it called, a mercenary. I hired myself out to the Roman,
you know, army. ובין גנזי רומי מצאתיה, U'vein ginzei Romi matzasiha, and
I found this in the storehouses of Rome, so from something obviously
they plundered when, you know, they took over Israel. וכתוב בה, V'chasuv
bah, and it was written in it, לאחר ארבעת אלפים ומאתים ותשעים
ואחת שנה לעולם, L'achar arba'as alafim u'masayim v'tishim v'achas shana l'olam, after
4,291 years, and the הגה Hagah has a different גירסא, girsa, but
anyway, 4,290 is almost exactly the same number we had before, 4,250.
Okay. העולם ייתום, Ha'olam yeisom, the world will finish. So this is
again about in the year 500, 550. מהן מלחמות תנינים, Mehen milchamos
taninim, some of it will come through wars of sea creatures like
the לווייתן. Livyasan. Some say that's a metaphor, it means wars of
like national superpowers. ומהן מלחמות גוג ומגוג, U'mehen milchamos Gog u'Magog, and
some it will be through the wars of גוג ומגוג. Gog u'Magog,
ושאר ימות המשיח, V'sha'ar yemos HaMashiach,
and the rest of that period of time after that's done, okay,
will be the time of משיח. Moshiach. ואין הקדוש ברוך הוא מחדש
את עולמו אלא לאחר שבעת אלפים שנה. V'ein HaKadosh Baruch Hu m'chadesh
es olamo ela l'achar shivas alafim shana. So this is like also
a question about what's the sequence. We thought that this whole idea
of destroying everything and rebuilding it like—where does משיח Moshiach come? Before
that? After that? So he is actually saying, you know, משיח Moshiach.
could come, you know, sometime in the year—in the middle of the—of
the
fifth
millennia—some—you know, sometimes after—after—after what was it, 4,290
years. But even if משיח Moshiach. comes during that time and you
have all the wars of גוג ומגוג, Gog u'Magog this whole idea
of creating a whole new world, that's not going to happen until
the end of 7,000 years. רב אחא בריה דרבא אמר לאחר חמשת
אלפים שנה, Rav Acha brei d'Rava amar l'achar chameshas alafim shana, after
5,000 years. Okay, that makes it a little more sense. You still
have the wars of גוג ומגוג and משיח Moshiach coming, you know,
coming first, but then in that period, you know, maybe they're going
to come in the year whatever, you know, in—in the beginning of
the fifth millennia and then the world will renew at the end
of the fifth millennia.
איתמר, Ismar, it was taught. Okay. תניא, we taught in a ברייתא,
Braisa, רבי נתן אומר, Rabbi Nasan omer, מקרא זה נוקב ויורד עד
התהום. mikra zeh nokeiv v'yored ad hatehom. Rabbi Nasan said
this verse pierces and goes down to the very depths.
So—what does he mean? Well let's see what the verse is. כי
עוד חזון למועד, Ki od chazon l'moed, because, you know, to the
vision is yet wait for its appointed time, ויפח לקץ v'yafei'ach lakeitz
and like blow towards or the—the end of days, ולא יכזב, v'lo
yechazeiv, and it will not lie.
I actually translated, you know, the ויפח לקץ v'yafei'ach lakeitz or ויפח
לקץ v'yapei'ach lakeitz as blow, that's what the גמרא Gemara will say
later, but probably the more פשט pshat translation there is like it
declares the end of times and it will not lie.
Okay. אם יתמהמה חכה לו, Im yis'mame'ah chakei lo, if it will
tarry you should wait for it. Obviously that's talk about משיח אף
על פי שיתמהמה עם כל זה אחכה לו. Mashiach af al pi
sheyis'mame'ah im kol zeh achakei lo. Okay. כי בוא יבוא, Ki vo
yavo, because it will certainly come, לא יאחר, lo ye'acher, and it
will not—it will not be delayed. Okay. So what does this mean?
לא כרבותינו שהיו דורשים, Lo k'raboseinu shehayu dorshim, not like our rabbis
that would explain that tried to compute the end of days based
on the פסוק pasuk in Daniel, עד עידן עידנין ופלג עידן, Ad
idan idanin u'plag idan,
until the time and times and half of time. So what does
that mean? So רש"י Rashi says here that the עידן idan means
time is 400 years, that's the period of exile in מצרים. Mitzrayim.
So one עידן, idan, two עידנין, idanin, that's three, that's 1,200 years,
and half an עידן idan is another 200, that's 1,400 years. So
1,400 years, you know, that's when משיח Moshiach will come. 1,400 years
from when? From the time of Daniel? Okay, so Daniel was right
before, you know, the second בית המקדש, Beis HaMikdash, that was understood
to
be— 420 years, so then you add another thousand, so then you're
about at the year 1000. So that's basically where 1400 years would
get you if you would get it from the time of דניאל,
Daniel, roughly to the year 1000. Okay, so not like that computation.
Where were we?
ולא כרבי שמלאי, V'lo k'rebi Simlai, and not like Rabbi Simlai, שהיה
דורש, she-haya doreish, האכלתם לחם דמעה ותשקמו בדמעות שליש, He-echaltam lechem dima
vatashkemo bidmaos shalish,
I have made them, fed them the bread of tears, and
have given them tears to drink in,
you know, in great number, in great measure, שליש shalish is a
measure. But רש"י Rashi says that this שליש shalish means a third.
So it's basically the same computation, which is that what they suffered
in the exile of Egypt—this is just the way רש"י Rashi reads
it—is 400 years. That is a third of what the ultimate exile
is going to be until משיח Moshiach. comes, so that would get
you basically 1200 years. But to make it even closer to the
previous computation, רש"י Rashi said that the two exiles, Egypt and בבל,
Bavel, 400 and 70, if those two are a third of the
ultimate exile afterwards, so you multiply that by three and you have
1410, which is basically exactly the same computation as before. And if
we're now counting the 1410 of exile from the חורבן הבית—I Churban
Habayis said before maybe we would count it from the time of
דניאל, Daniel, but that would get you to the year... if we
counted from the חורבן הבית, Churban Habayis, that would get you about
to the year 1500. Okay,
but anyway, not like those two. Now, אלא, ela, but rather... where
were we? Excuse me, ולא, I skipped, ולא כרבי עקיבא, v'lo k'rebi
Akiva, and also not like Rabbi Akiva, שהיה דורש, she-haya doreish, who
would explain the פסוק, pasuk, עוד אחת מעט. Od achas me'at. עוד
אחת מעט, Od achas me'at, just a little more time, in, you
know, one more little thing, ואני מרעיש את השמים ואת הארץ, va-ani
mar'ish es hashamayim v'es ha'aretz, and I will cause the heaven and
earth to be, you know,
tumultuous because of the bringing of משיח. Moshiach Now, what was Rabbi
Akiva? So Rabbi Akiva
was a believer in Barkochba, so presumably the way—this isn't exactly what
רש"י Rashi says, but presumably what the גמרא Gemara. means is that
Rabbi Akiva read the פסוק Pasuk, like a little bit after the
חורבן הבית, Churban Habayis, that's when משיח Moshiach is gonna come, and
that's why he believed that Barkochba was the משיח. Moshiach? Now going
back to the original
פסוק, pasuk the מהרש"א Maharsha has a brilliant read. You know, the
מהרש"א says, כי עוד חזון למועד ki od chazon lamo'eid means the
word עד עידן עידנין eid idan idanim is מועד. mo'eid. So that's
saying it's another vision of what this מועד mo'eid means, not the
way you guys have been interpreting it. There's another, the מועד mo'eid
means something else. ויפח לקץ, v'yapuach lakeitz, and blow away, that does,
the words don't exactly fit, but basically, and this other interpretation about
a third, that also is, you know, is not going to happen.
And then the best part about it is the last, ולא יכזב,
v'lo yechazeiv, and it also is not Barkochba, because Barkochba's name, at
least the way the rabbis refer to him, was בר כוזיבא. Bar
Koziva. So it's not the עד עידן עידנין eid idan idanim and
it's not בר כוזיבא, Bar Koziva, none of those are going to
be the משיח. Moshiach. Okay, and what he means by saying that
it would pierce and go down to the depths, you know, it
could be that sounds like this is so deeply painful and hurtful,
but that doesn't make sense. What's hurtful about that? Maybe he's just
saying the rabbis are thinking they're so smart and trying to figure
it out and this shows us like, no, you know, you haven't
reached the depths of the matter. This is, or another way רש"י
Rashi explains this is that this is something like fathomless, you're never
going to get to the bottom of this, don't even try. Okay,
אלא, ela, but let's finish up that point of the גמרא. Gemara
So it's not like all these rabbis thought. אלא מלכות ראשון שבעים
שנה, מלכות שנייה חמישים ושתים, Ela malchus rishon shivim shana, malchus shniya
chamishim u-shtayim, but, you know,
in the time of the בית המקדש, Beis Hamikdash, the way רש"י
Rashi reads it, there was a kingship of 70 years, which was
בית חשמונאי Beis Chashmonai or the successful part of בית חשמונאי. Beis
Chashmonai. There was then a kingship of 52 years, which was Herod,
ומלכות בן כוזיבא שתי שנים
ומחצה, u-malchus Ben Koziva shteiy shanim u-mechtza, and Barkochba for two and
a half years. Now, how is that a retort to what just
came before is not clear, but the way at least the מהרש"א
reads it, he says not like Rabbi Akiva who thought that it
meant that after a little bit, then משיח Moshiach will come and
that's Barkochba. No, because we had—it means after all of these little,
you know, sparks of self-sovereignty what happened, and that will all pass
and משיח Moshiach will come after all of that, so even after
Barkochba, not that Barkochba is the משיח. Moshiach But anyway. Not exactly
clear how that was in conversation with what just came right before.
Okay, אמר רבי שמואל בר נחמני אמר רבי יונתן. Amar Rabi Shmuel
bar Nachmani Amar Rabi Yonasan. I'm sorry, I skipped a line. מה
ויפח לקץ? Mah Vayafayach Laketz? What does it mean 'declare the end'
or 'blow the end' ולא יכזב V'lo Yekazev
and it will not lie? אמר רבי שמואל בר נחמני אמר רבי
יונתן: Amar Rabi Shmuel bar Nachmani Amar Rabi Yonasan: תיפח עצמן של
מחשבי קיצין. Tipach Atzman Shel Mechashvei Kitzin. Let blasted be the bones
of those who try to compute the end of days. שהיו אומרים
כיון שהגיע הקץ ולא בא שוב אינו בא. Shehayu Omerim Keivan Shehigia
Haketz V'lo Ba Shuv Eino Ba.
Because they would say they computed when it's going to happen and
then משיח Moshiach? doesn't come, so they're going to say, 'Oh, so
משיח Mashiach will never come.' So ויפח לקץ Vayafayach Laketz means blow
like destroy like
they should be laid to naught all those who try to figure
out the end of time ולא יכזב V'lo Yekazev to not turn
because they're all just going to be turned into liars. They're going
to say it's going to come and it's not going to come
and then they'll say it'll never come. So get rid of all
of that foolishness and all that stuff that makes them all into
liars. And then going back to the rest of the פסוק, אלא
חכה לו. Ela Chakei Lo.
Just stop trying to be a whole חכם Chacham and figure out
when it's going to come. Just wait for it כנאמר אם יתמהמה
חכה לו, Kene-emar Im Yitmahameah Chakei Lo, if it will tarry wait
for him. שמא תאמר אנו מחכים והוא אינו מחכה. Shema Tomar Anu
Mechakim V'hu Eino Mechakeh. Lest you say okay, we're waiting, but is
God trying to bring the משיח? Mashiach Is God eager for this
time והוא אינו מחכה תלמוד לומר לכן יחכה ה' לחננכם ולכן ירום
לרחמכם. V'hu Eino Mechakeh Talmud Lomar Lachen Yechakeh Hashem L'chananchem V'lachen Yarom
L'rachamchem. No,
therefore God will wait,
will tarry,
pine for, look towards, not tarry, pine for to do to be
kind to you and to be compassionate to you. God is also
trying to bring the משיח. Mashiach? וכי מאחר שאנו מחכים, V'chi Me-acher
She-anu Mechakim, we're waiting for the משיח Mashiach והוא מחכה, V'hu Mechakeh,
and God's waiting, מי מעכב? Mi Me-akev? Who's stopping the משיח Mashiach
from coming? מדת הדין מעכבת. Midat Ha-din Me-akevet. Justice is stopping it.
Everybody wants it to happen, but we have to earn it. וכי
מאחר שמדת הדין מעכבת אנו למה מחכים? V'chi Me-acher She-midat Ha-din Me-akevet
Anu Lama Mechakim? So if that's stopping it, why is it important
for us to wait for it?
Meaning if it's not like it's going to be—this is actually a
very deep question. What's the point of, as we talked before, does
waiting for the
משיח mashiach distract you from the work in this world?
Is all the computations—you see there was a reality of people trying
to compute it and for the most part the גמרא Gemara pushing
back against it and saying it's not helping trying to compute. You
wind up giving people false hope, you wind up distracting yourself from
the work that you need to be doing. Okay, so fine. So
we're not going to try to compute it. Should we still have
that sense of longing for the coming of משיח? mashiach So that's
basically what the גמרא Gemara is asking. If it's not going to
come because we pray hard and it's not going to come just
because we long for it, it's not going to be like something
that God is going to bring without us being deserving, if the
מדת הדין Midat Ha-din is מעכב, Me-akev, if we have to be
deserving, then why should we be waiting for something? Let's work to
earn it. Let's actually focus on being deserving. So what's the point
of being מחכה? Mechakeh? So
למה
מחכים?
Lama Mechakim?
לקבל שכר, Lekabel Sachar, to receive reward שנאמר אשרי כל חוכי לו.
Shene-emar Ashrei Kol Chochei Lo. Praised are all those who wait for
it. So yes, there is a value of pining, of waiting for
it, because it shows ultimately a belief in an ultimate redemption. So
it's striking that balance between having faith, having belief, working for a
better world because you believe ultimately we can get to a redeemed
world, but not having it completely preoccupy you that it takes you
away from the work you need to be doing. אמר אביי: לא
פחות עלמיא מתלתין ושיתא צדיקי. Lo Pachot Almaya Mi-tlatin V'shita Tzadikim. Famous
statement of Abaye. The world has no less than thirty-six צדיקים Tzadikim
דמקבלי אפי שכינה בכל דרא, D'mekablei Appei Shechina B'chol Dara, that they
receive God's countenance in every generation. Okay, that's the ל"ו צדיקים. Lamed
Vav Tzadikim. שנאמר אשרי כל חוכי לו, Shene-emar Ashrei Kol Chochei Lo,
praise are all that wait for Him. לו בגימטריא תלתין ושיתא הוי.
Lo B'gematria Tlatin V'shita Havei. It's thirty-six, the גימטריא Gematria of לו—למד
ו"ו. So the thirty-six צדיקים Tzadikim in every generation. והאמר רבא דרא
דקמי קודשא בריך הוא תמני סרי אלפי פרסא? Ve-ha-amar Rava Dara De-kamei
Kudsha Brich Hu Tamnei Srei Alfei Parsa? But doesn't Rava say that
the row of people that are present before God are imagining a
place up in heaven where God is in the center and all
the souls of everybody are before God and that row of people
that stands before God is eighteen thousand פרסאות Parsa'ot long שנאמר סביב
שמונה עשר אלף. Shene-emar Saviv Shmonah Asar Alef. Around
him eighteen thousand. לא קשיא. Lo Kashya. It's
not difficult. הא דמסתכלי
באספקלריא המאירה והא דלא מסתכלי באספקלריא המאירה. Ha D'mistaklei B'ispaklaria Ha-meirah V'ha
De-la Mistaklei B'ispaklaria Ha-meirah. God through a like a clear
lens, a lens that gives off light.
אספקלריא ispaklaria could be mirror, but mirror doesn't make sense here, unless
it's reflecting God's whatever. Anyway, but through a through like a clear
lens and the other see God through a cloudy lens. Okay, but
36 are the ones that are the closest to God, which Abaye's
statement of דרא, dara, which I translated as בכל דור bechol dor
in every generation, which sort of fits with, you know, with the
context, but Rava uses the word דרא dara to mean a row
of those sitting in the presence of God. So here he might
mean in this front row, you know, is but בכל דור bechol
dor makes it sound every generation. Anyway, so now it says like
this, ומי נפישי כולי
האי, u'mi nefishei kulei hai, are really, you know, they're that many
צדיקים tzaddikim that see God directly that are right there in God's
presence, 36? והאמר חזקיה אמר רבי ירמיה משום שמעון בן יוחי, v'ha'amar
Chizkiyah amar Rabbi Yirmeyah mishum Shimon bar Yochai, but doesn't Chizkiyah say
in the name of Rabbi Yirmeyah in
the
name of Shimon bar Yochai, ראיתי בני עלייה, ra'iti bnei aliyah, I
have seen those of stature, of high spiritual stature, והן מועטין, v'hen
muatin, and they're very few? Presumably this is like when he was
in the cave, you know. שאם אלף הם, she'im elef hem, if
there are a thousand, אני ובני מהם, ani u'vni mehem, I and
my son, who were in that cave, you know, and separated out
from the world, we are among them. אם מאה הם, im meah
hem, if there are a hundred, אני ובני מהם. ani u'vni mehem.
אם שנים הם, im shnayim hem, אני ובני הם. ani u'vni hem.
And if there's only two, me and my son are they. Now
what the purpose of is saying that and he's how did he
know that he and his son were at the highest level? But
anyway, for us what's relevant is that it could be even a
very tiny number are really, you know, called בני עלייה, bnei aliyah,
those of stature. And Abaye says there are 36. So the גמרא
says, לא קשיא, lo kashya, it's not difficult, הא דעיילי בבר הא
דעיילי בלא בר. ha d'ayli b'bar ha d'ayli b'lo bar. There are
the 30, you know, there are those that have to that have
to ask permission before they enter in the presence of God, and
those are 36, and the possibility that the number of the righteous
are so small that they're even as little as two, those would
be the numbers that would have that would enter, have the right
to enter in God's presence even without permission. Whatever any of this
means. Okay, now, אמר רב, said Rav, כלו כל הקיצין, kalu kol
ha-kitzin, back to trying to compute the end of days, all of
the end of days that have been computed have run out, so
it wasn't the year 1400 before, but anyway, ואין הדבר תלוי אלא
בתשובה ומעשים טובים. v'ein ha-davar talui ela b'teshuvah u'ma'asim tovim. And the
only way we're going to now get it is not because of
some prefixed time, you know, but because of the work we got
to do. תשובה ומעשים טובים, teshuvah u'ma'asim tovim, focusing on our תשובה
teshuvah and our good works. ושמואל אמר, u'Shmuel amar, and Shmuel said,
דיו לאבל שיעמוד באבלו, daiyo l'avel she'ya'amod b'evlo, it is enough for
the mourner to stay this long in his state of mourning, meaning
we have suffered long enough and in the end God will bring
the משיח even if we don't do תשובה, teshuvah, seems to be
what he is saying. And that's will be right now segueing us
into exactly this debate: will the משיח come regardless or only if
we earn it?
כתנאי, k'tana'ei, this is like a debate of תנאים. Tannaim. רבי אליעזר
אומר, Rabbi Eliezer omer, אם ישראל עושים תשובה נגאלים ואם לאו אין
נגאלים, im Yisrael osim teshuvah nigalin v'im lav ein nigalin, only if
the Jewish people do תשובה teshuvah will they be redeemed, if not
they will not be redeemed. אמר לו רבי יהושע, amar lo Rabbi
Yehoshua, Rabbi Joshua said back, אם אין עושים תשובה אין נגאלים, im
ein osim teshuvah ein nigalin, you mean to tell me you think
if they don't do תשובה teshuvah they'll never be redeemed, so there
will never be
משיח? אלא אמר הקדוש ברוך הוא מעמיד להם מלך שגזירותיו קשות כהמן,
ela amar Ha-Kadosh Baruch Hu ma'amid lahem melech she-gzeirotav kashot k'Haman, God
will make them do תשובה, teshuvah, God will, you know, rise up
against them a king who is as evil as Haman,
וישראל עושים תשובה ומחזירם למוטב, v'Yisrael osim teshuvah u'machziram l'mutav, and as
a result of these external threats, that will cause people us to
do תשובה teshuvah and that'll make us do better. Now, he does
not say we will do תשובה, teshuvah, that משיח will come without
תשובה, teshuvah, but it's just that it will come without us having
really, you know, being a true תשובה teshuvah and coming from our
own remorse and our own commitment. Whatever, it's going to come because
it's forced upon us. So God is committed to getting משיח here
regardless, and if we're not going to do it ourselves, he's going
to make us do it. Okay, so so that seems to be
the debate, and not whether you really don't need תשובה teshuvah at
all. Okay, so let's take a, but but is God committed to
bringing it regardless?
Okay, תניא אידך, tanya idach, we learned another
ברייתא, braita, רבי אליעזר אומר אם ישראל עושים תשובה נגאלים שנאמר שובו
בנים שובבים ארפא משובותיכם, Rabbi Eliezer omer im Yisrael osim teshuvah nigalin
shenemar shuvu banim shovavim erpa meshuvoteichem, only if they do תשובה teshuvah
will they be redeemed, as it says,
return wayward children, I will heal you. אמר לו רבי יהושע, amar
lo Rabbi Yehoshua, Rabbi Yehoshua said to him, והלא כבר נאמר, v'halo
kvar nemar, but doesn't it already say, חנם נמכרתם ולא בכסף תגאלו,
chinam nimkartem v'lo b'khesef tiga'elu, you have been sold for naught and
you won't be redeemed with money. חנם נמכרתם, chinam nimkartem, you've been
sold for naught, בעבודה זרה, b'avodah zarah, you traded off your your
your whole life for nothingness, for עבודה זרה. avodah zarah. ולא בכסף
תגאלו, v'lo b'khesef tiga'elu, but in the end you won't be redeemed
with money, means לא בתשובה ומעשים טובים, lo b'teshuvah u'ma'asim tovim, your
redemption will not come as a result of your תשובה teshuvah and
מעשים טובים. ma'asim tovim. So this sounds a little bit more that
Rabbi Yehoshua is saying that תשובה teshuvah and that even without any
תשובה teshuvah and מעשים טובים. ma'asim tovim. That even without any תשובה
teshuvah and מעשים טובים maasim tovim you will be redeemed. But to
reconcile it, we could be totally wicked and God will bring the
משיח because the time has finally come. But to reconcile it with
the previous statement of Rabbi Yehoshua and also and also with the
פסוקים pesukim because there are פסוקים pesukim that talk about doing תשובה,
teshuvah, if we want to harmonize, the best reading would be that
he would be saying even if we're not going to do it
ourselves, ultimately God will make us do it and it'll be a
תשובה teshuvah that'll be brought upon us by God. But it's not
through our own self-initiated תשובה ומעשים טובים teshuvah u'maasim tovim or it
doesn't have to come through that. אמר ליה רבי אליעזר לרבי יהושע.
Amar lei Rabbi Eliezer le'Rabbi Yehoshua. So now we're going to go
back and forth trying to quote פסוקים. pesukim. Rabbi Eliezer said to
Rabbi Yehoshua, והלא כבר נאמר vehalo kvar neemar doesn't it already say
שובו אלי ואשובה אליכם, shuvu elai ve'ashuva aleichem, if you return to
me I will return to you? אמר ליה רבי יהושע Amar lei
Rabbi Yehoshua והלא כבר נאמר vehalo kvar neemar כי אנכי בעלתי בכם
ki anochi ba'alti bachem because I have taken ownership over you ולקחתי
אתכם אחד מעיר ושניים ממשפחה, velakachti etchem echad me'ir ushnayim mimishpacha, one
from a city and two from a family, meaning I'm sort of
like going to grab onto you and force you even against your
will והבאתי אתכם ציון. veheveti etchem tzion. אמר ליה רבי אליעזר, Amar
lei Rabbi Eliezer, Rabbi Eliezer said, והלא כבר נאמר, vehalo kvar neemar,
behold, here's another פסוק that you need to do תשובה, teshuvah, בשובה
ונחת תיוושעון beshuva vanachat tivashe'un with returning and pleasure, or you know,
anyway reading שובה shuva here as תשובה, teshuvah, you will be saved.
אמר ליה רבי יהושע לרבי אליעזר Amar lei Rabbi Yehoshua le'Rabbi Eliezer
והלא כבר נאמר vehalo kvar neemar כה אמר ה' גואל ישראל קדושו
ko amar Hashem goel Yisrael kedosho so says God the Redeemer of
Israel לבזה נפש למתעב גוי לעבד מושלים livzoh nefesh le'mita'ev goy le'eved
moshlim to the one who has been despised to the you know
lowly of soul despised by nations slave to masters מלכים יראו וקמו
שרים וישתחוו, melachim yiru ve'kamu sarim ve'yishtachavu,
kings will rise up and bow down you know and and officers
and prostrate themselves or kings will rise up and officers prostrate themselves.
So that means that you know that even if you are in
a despised state nonetheless I will redeem you. So again what we
have here is I mean you know Rabbi Eliezer's position is clear.
You gotta תשובה teshuvah you know and that was also רב's position.
But שמואל's Shmuel position about how long you know is the אבל
avel going to remain in his אבלות aveilut and Rabbi Yehoshua's position
is a little less clear. Are they saying that you'll be redeemed
when the God will ultimately there has to come a time and
God will redeem us even if we are totally in our state
of wickedness or God will bring external forces that will force us
to better our ways and then משיח will come? We will continue
with this tomorrow.